Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at the anti-aging properties
of the diabetes drug, Metformin.
The noxious weed goat's rue
was widely used
as an herbal medicine
back in the Middle Ages for
thirst and frequent urination,
what we now know of
as a cardinal symptom
and sign of diabetes.
The plant produces
a mitochondrial poison
known as galegine.
One can imagine
how this could help discourage
grazing herbivores,
but why would crippling
mitochondrial function
help with diabetes?
Well, if you got the dose
just right,
you could impair
energy production just enough
to spring AMPK into action.
AMPK would then dial down
the liver's
energy-intensive process
of sugar production,
and blood sugars would fall.
Galegine proved too toxic
for use in humans
(and presumably goats)
but was tweaked
into a milder form in the 1950s.
That's the origin story
of metformin,
now, even 60+ years later
the most widely prescribed
diabetes drug in the world.
Sold originally as Glucophage
(meaning "sugar eater"),
metformin is
now prescribed annually
more than 90 million times
in the U.S. alone.
Despite all the strides
in biotechnology,
Big Pharma has yet
to come up with a safer,
more effective
first-line treatment
for type 2 diabetes
than a drug
that retails
at pennies per pill.
Ramping up AMPK
isn't all that metformin does
(for example, it also appears
to foster the growth
of good bacteria
in the gut).
But the AMPK boost alone
would be expected
to have
wide-ranging health effects.
Remember, AMPK is activated
when resources are scarce;
so, it causes the body
to hunker down
into energy-conservation mode
and put the brakes
on new construction projects.
So, no more making excess
blood sugar or cholesterol.
Time to start tapping
into the larder.
And, indeed, metformin doesn't
just lower sugars in the blood
but cholesterol and body fat.
And shutting down
the excess synthesis of proteins
can also have health benefits.
Fibrosis is the accumulation
of scar tissue
in response
to an inflammatory insult.
As a transient,
localized phenomenon,
fibrosis helps heal wounds
and repair damaged tissue,
but in response to the systemic
inflammation of aging,
surplus scar tissue
can build up in our heart,
liver, kidneys, and lungs.
Excess fibrosis is estimated
to contribute to 45 percent
of all death
in the United States.
But AMPK switches the body
into miser mode,
shrinking the energy budget
for such superfluous activities
and ratchets down
fibrotic processes.
The AMPK priorities shift
from growth to preservation
might also be expected
to slow cancer progression.
Based on dozens
of observational studies
involving tens of thousands
of diabetic cancer patients,
those on metformin
did indeed experience
a significant
survival advantage,
correlating with
a 26 percent decreased risk
of dying from cancer.
No wonder there are
more than 100 ongoing studies
to put metformin
to the test against cancer.
As the director of Harvard's
Cancer Center put it,
"Metformin may have
already saved more people
from cancer deaths
than any drug in history."
If AMPK plays such a key role
in the aging process,
and metformin boosts AMPK,
can metformin slow aging
and lengthen lifespans?
It certainly can
in some species.
C. elegans worms fed metformin
maintained a youthful state
and can exhibit
a nearly 40 percent increase
in average survival.
Interfere with
the AMPK pathway, though,
and this
lifespan extension disappears,
confirming the role of AMPK
in metformin's
anti-aging effects.
Metformin also improves
the healthspans
and lifespans of mice,
but failed to extend
the lives of rats,
calling the pro-longevity
effects of metformin
into question.
The dose they used
(15 times that used in humans)
may have been too high, however,
and the F344 rats they used
are an inbred strain
(named after the 344th
brother sister mating)
that are resistant
to the health benefits
of calorie restriction.
Since metformin
acts through AMPK
as a calorie
restriction mimetic,
it stands to reason
that these animals
may be less prone
to metformin's effects.
What about humans?
Unlike other potential
anti-aging drugs
in the pipeline,
we have the benefit of data
on more than
a million study subjects
who have been tracked
in metformin trials.
And, indeed,
compared to diabetics
who take drugs
other than metformin,
those on metformin
appear protected
from age-related
susceptibilities,
like fractures,
or serious infections,
glaucoma,
and cognitive impairment.
Most importantly,
diabetics who take metformin
live significantly longer
than those taking different
blood sugar-lowering drugs.
Doesn't that prove metformin
is a pro-longevity drug?
No.
For example, maybe metformin
just controlled
their diabetes better.
Researchers still found
a survival benefit
for diabetics on metformin
compared to those
as well managed on other drugs,
but maybe the other drugs
were shortening lifespans,
and so, metformin
just looked good in comparison.
How could you try
to tease out the effects?
What if you
compared the lifespans
of diabetics on metformin
to nondiabetics?
Now, that's not really
a fair comparison.
Any benefits metformin has
could easily
be outweighed and masked
by the life-limiting
nature of diabetes--
unless, that is,
the diabetics on metformin
actually lived longer.
Longer than nondiabetics.
And,
are you sitting down?
That's exactly
what the research shows.
Diabetics placed on metformin
went on to live longer lives
than those who never
got diabetes in the first place.
From a longevity standpoint,
it's as if they got lucky
to be diagnosed with diabetes,
because then, they had access
to this lifespan-enhancing drug.
So, wait.
If metformin is so powerful
as to more than offset
such a dreaded diagnosis,
should everyone
be taking metformin?
What are the downsides?
That's exactly what
I'm gonna be covering next.
The apparent
reductions in mortality
from all causes put together
and diseases of aging
associated with metformin use
suggest that the drug metformin
could be extending
life and healthspans
by acting as a geroprotective,
or anti-aging, agent.
What might the downsides be?
Gastrointestinal side-effects,
such as flatulence,
indigestion,
and abdominal discomfort,
are relatively common.
More than half
starting metformin
report diarrhea, for example,
and a quarter experience
nausea or vomiting.
About 10 percent
unknowingly taking the placebo
report similar symptoms, though;
so, the actual
proportion of people
suffering such symptoms
due to the drug
is probably more like 1 in 3.
Most of these effects
tend to be transient, though,
and can be minimized
by taking metformin with food
and starting
at a suboptimal dose,
increasing gradually to target
over a period of weeks.
Once-a-day
extended-release versions
also tend to be more tolerable.
The most dreaded
side effect, though,
is lactic acidosis,
the potentially fatal buildup
of acid in the blood.
I mean,
poisoning of the mitochondria
is kind of the whole point.
That's what activates AMPK,
but it's supposed to be a mild
mitochondrial poison,
but sometimes it evidently
poisons a bit too much.
Thankfully,
metformin-induced
lactic acidosis
is extremely rare.
It has a fatality rate
of 50 percent
but only occurs
at a rate of about
0.03 cases
per thousand patient-years.
That means
taking metformin for a year
only has about a 1 in 67,000
chance of killing you.
Lactic acidosis
is primarily caused
by insufficient metformin
clearance by the kidneys;
so, risk can be minimized by,
for example,
temporarily stopping the drug
while undergoing procedures
that put the kidneys at risk,
such as major surgery
or intravenous contrast dyes
used for certain
imaging procedures.
Those with
mild to moderate kidney disease
can still benefit from metformin
at an adjusted dose.
Elderly individuals
should have their
kidney function tested
before starting metformin,
and regularly monitored.
Excess alcohol consumption
is also believed
to increase the risk
of fatal metformin-induced
lactic acidosis.
One of the more
insidious side effects
is B12 deficiency,
vitamin B12 deficiency,
affecting as many
as one in three
long-term metformin users,
but can start
as early as a few months.
The mechanism is still unclear,
but routine monitoring of B12
status has been recommended,
and B12 supplementation
has been suggested.
Another adverse consequence
of metformin
is less side effect
than main effect.
Remember how metformin
is a mild mitochondrial poison?
The way metformin boosts AMPK
is by impairing our body's
ability to produce energy.
What might that mean
for athletic performance?
Healthy men and women
were found to suffer
a significant decline
in peak aerobic capacity
after only about
a week on metformin.
The average hit was only
three percent, though,
which could be meaningful
for an elite athlete
but would be unlikely to impede
recreational physical activity.
However, some individuals
lost as much as 10 percent,
which could
be noticeably fatiguing.
Note these detriments
were only found
at or near maximal workloads,
and so, most active individuals
would be unlikely
to experience an impairment
in routine activity.
Over the long term, though,
metformin may undercut
physical fitness.
Older adults were randomized
to 12 weeks
of supervised aerobic exercise
on or off metformin.
They trained for 45 minutes
three times a week
on a treadmill,
bike, or elliptical,
ramping up to a vigorous target
of 85 percent
of their maximal heart rate.
Unfortunately, metformin
attenuated the improvement
in physiological function
after exercise training.
Cardiovascular fitness
is so important;
yet, after three months,
metformin cut their improvement
in cardiorespiratory fitness
in half compared to placebo,
though this didn't reach
statistical significance.
Metformin did, however,
significantly
blunt their improvement
in whole-body
insulin sensitivity
which normally improves
with physical activity.
Aerobic exercise, (or "cardio")
is critical for maintaining
cardiovascular fitness,
whereas resistance exercise
(also known
as strength training,
for example,
with weights or bands)
is essential for maintaining
muscle mass as we age.
In 2019,
the so-called MASTERS trial
was published,
investigating what metformin
might do to muscle gains,
and, the title of the paper
gives it away:
"Metformin blunts
muscle hypertrophy
in response to progressive
resistance exercise training
in older adults."
After 14 weeks of progressive
resistance training,
men and women
in the placebo group
accrued significant
lean body mass,
but those randomized
to the metformin group did not.
For example,
about a four percent gain
in thigh muscle mass
in the placebo group
versus virtually none
in the metformin group.
The differences
in strength, however,
did not reach
statistical significance.
So, might the benefits
of metformin
outweigh the risks for expanding
the healthspan and lifespan
of even nondiabetics?
The investigators
reviewing the evidence
that diabetics
taking metformin lived longer,
on average, than nondiabetics,
concluded their
"results suggest that metformin
could be an effective
intervention
to extend
the lifespan of people
who do not have diabetes."
You can't know, though,
until you put it to the test,
which I'll explore, next.
Given the evidence
that diabetics
taking the drug metformin
may live longer
than people who
don't even have diabetes
suggests metformin
has an anti-aging effect,
slowing the diseases of aging
and, in doing so,
extending both
health and lifespans,
but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
There are a few small,
brief trials of metformin
on healthy volunteers,
for example,
randomizing
a dozen or so individuals
to metformin
or placebo for a few weeks,
comparing the effects
on muscle and fat biopsies.
Beneficial changes
in gene expression
in various
aging pathways were noted,
along with objective
improvements in risk factors,
such as LDL cholesterol
and triglycerides,
but what we'd really like
are hard endpoints,
like disease outcomes and death.
Enter the TAME trial,
Targeting Aging with Metformin.
Spearheaded by the nonprofit
American Federation
for Aging Research,
TAME has the ambitious goal
of randomizing 3,000
nondiabetic individuals
aged 65-79
to metformin or placebo
over a period of six years
to assess the effect
on age-related conditions,
such as heart attacks,
stroke,
cancer,
dementia,
and death.
Current treatments
"just exchange one disease
for another," railed
the principal investigator.
Someone cured of cancer
may just drop dead the next year
from a heart attack.
"What we want to show
is that if we delay aging,
that's the best way
to delay disease."
Sadly,
though the TAME trial
received FDA approval in 2015,
it has yet
to get off the ground.
You can guess why.
As the editor-in-chief
of an anti-aging journal put it,
"There is no way in hell
to make money out of it."
Metformin's patent
expired decades ago,
and generics retail
at pennies a pill.
It's considered
a "genuinely good use
of 75 million dollars,"
but the researchers
have only evidently
been able to raise $11 million
from private donors.
Some in Silicon Valley
tech circles
aren't waiting for the results.
Apparently, some techies
have started taking metformin
in a bid to live longer,
though it's only officially
available by prescription
for diabetes.
Metformin is cheap,
relatively safe,
and one of the most
promising drugs to combat
age-related diseases,
but there are reasons
to temper our expectations.
Though it's been referred
to as a "magic drug,"
the longevity benefits in mice
were small and dose dependent.
At best, it may increase
the average lifespan
of certain mice by five percent,
but at a higher dose,
actually shortens lifespan.
Much of the enthusiasm
for the TAME trial
rests on it acting
as a test case
to successfully get regulatory
authorities, like the FDA,
to formally recognize
any treatment
for the aging process itself,
in hopes that this will
arouse Big Pharma
to invest large-scale R&D
to advance the field.
Further reservations
about the panacean prospects
placed on metformin
arise from the landmark
Diabetes
Prevention Program study
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine.
Thousands of prediabetic
individuals were randomized
to metformin
or placebo for years
to see if the drug
could prevent their prediabetes
from turning
into full-blown diabetes.
It worked,
reducing overall
diabetes incidence by 31 percent
compared to placebo,
but it didn't for everyone.
For example, it didn't appear
to significantly benefit
those 60 years or older
and only seemed
to help those most at risk--
those with class II obesity
and the highest blood sugars.
Those with lower
(but still elevated)
blood sugars,
and those under a BMI of 35
did not have their diabetes risk
significantly dampened
by the drug.
One small study even found that,
while metformin alleviated
the insulin resistance
of diabetics
and those with
a family history of diabetes,
metformin actually worsened
the insulin resistance
(the cause of prediabetes
and type 2 diabetes)
of nondiabetic obese individuals
that didn't have
a genetic predisposition.
If you have diabetes,
it can make things better;
if you don't,
it may make things worse.
So, healthier individuals
may not reap the benefits
of metformin
that some try to extrapolate
from those
longevity studies on diabetics.
In fact, even those researchers
are explicit that
they don't think metformin
is ready for prime time
as an anti-aging intervention
by the general population.
What's safer
and works even better?
There was a third arm
of the Diabetes Prevention
Program study.
Thousands of prediabetics
were randomized
to metformin or placebo
or lifestyle changes--
a cholesterol-lowering
low-fat diet and exercise,
at least about 20 minutes a day
moderate intensity exercise,
such as brisk walking.
Compared to the placebo group,
those taking metformin
were 31 percent less likely
to develop diabetes.
The lifestyle group
was 58 percent less likely.
Making simple lifestyle changes
was nearly
twice as effective as metformin
(and with fewer side effects--
for example,
six times fewer cases
of gastrointestinal distress).
Other randomized
controlled trials
have found the same thing--
lifestyle approaches superior
to drug-based approaches
for diabetes prevention.
And, that 60 or so percent
drop in risk was not among those
who actually made
the lifestyle change,
just those instructed to do so.
Another diabetes
prevention trial
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine
that found the same
58 percent reduction
in diabetes risk
among those asked
to make lifestyle changes
drilled down to see
what the benefit was
for those who fully complied.
Only a fraction
of the lifestyle
intervention group
met the modest goals.
Only about a third
increased their exercise,
for example.
Only about a quarter
met the minimum
recommended intake of fiber
(found concentrated
in whole plant foods)
or cut down
on enough saturated fat
(mostly dairy, dessert,
chicken, and pork).
But, they did better
than the control group,
and fewer of them developed
diabetes because of it.
But, what if you look
just at the folks
who actually made all
(or even just 4 out of 5)
of the recommended
lifestyle changes?
They had zero diabetes--
none of them got diabetes
over the course of the study,
meaning effectively
a 100 percent drop in risk.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.